In the previous lesson we had a look at generics and we touched briefly upon generic constraints
with this log length method.
In this lesson we're going to do a deeper dive into generic constraints in TypeScript.
So generics gives us flexibility but sometimes we need to add rules.
Generic constraints lets us to exactly that keep flexibility without squeezing safety.
To let's start with a problem, generics allow any type but sometimes that freedom is too much.
A generic constraint restricts the types that a generic can accept.
It tells TypeScript that T must follow these rules.
Basically we do T extends some type.
The key word extends is used to apply constraints.
So let's have a look at an interface.
You can do interface as length, now length, be a number.
This interface defines a rule, anything with a length property.
Let's now rewrite this log length method to use our has length interface.
To do function log length, T extends as length.
Our value is coming in of type T and our function returns void.
Now we're going to console log value.length.
So the value length is coming from our has length interface here.
The TypeScript guarantees that the value has a length property.
So you can do log length and say hello, world, world, to log length and have an array
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 and we had a look at this in our previous lesson.
We can do log length and we can give it maybe an object and say length is 10.
Let's execute this.
Let's just click the log and execute it and we have our three logs here.
All of these are going to work because they satisfy the constraint.
They've all got a length property.
If we change this object down here, let's say we remove this and we provide a value of
number here, let me get an error because the number does not have a length property.
So TypeScript is going to block this, but let's now have a look at a more realistic
example.
Let's just move this code here.
Let's have a function, get ID, miss a t extends and now we're going to dynamically or create
our type on the fly and we're going to do this in curly braces.
We're going to say this type has a number property.
Now we provide our parameters and item, it's going to be our type t, our function is going
to return number.
Now if we do return item, notice we now have this ID because we defined it up here.
So this function is going to work with any object as long as it has an ID property.
So we can do, for example, get ID and we can pass an object with the ID of one and maybe
name of Alice, that's absolutely fine because this object has this ID property.
If we try to get ID, this time we're just going to supply our object, but we're not going
to provide the ID, we're just going to say name equals bob and notice we get this squarely
underline here and it's complaining that we haven't supplied the ID in this particular
object.
So this pattern here, let's get ID, is extremely common in APIs and database code.
You can also use multiple constraints by combining interfaces.
So let's see an example of that, we do interface, let's say has ID, ID and number and
maybe have interface as name, name, string, that's now define a function to use this.
So let's say print entity, have a t type t, which is going to extend, extends our has
ID, but it also is going to extend has name.
As a reminder, we can do this by doing the app assigned and then has name for the seconds
interface.
Now we have our parameters, so if you have an entity of type t, which is our combined
has ID and has name and the function is going to return void.
Now we can put our body of our function to console log into entity.id and maybe entity.name.
So the type bus satisfy base interfaces, the constraints also work with classes as we move
this again.
And so up class and say user, let's build a constructor, a public parameters ID and number,
empty implementation, I'm going to do a function, I'm going to say log user type t is going
to extend our user class, and we're going to supply a user of type t, function is going to
return void, the console log user dot ID.
So this ensures the generic type is user or any subclass of user.
Now without constraints, generics can be rather too loose, but with comp with constraints
they're becoming super powerful and safe, but when to use generic constraints, I suggest
use generics constraints when you need flexibility, but with rules, your functional works
with related types, you want safer, reasonable utilities, or maybe your building libraries
or frameworks.